{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man’s general Ventidius [ven-TID-ee-uss] drove the Parthians [PAR-thee-uns] out of\nAsia Minor. His wife Fulvia [FULL-vee-uh] led a faction of senators during a civil war. This\nman was the target of Cicero’s [SISS-ur-oh’s] Philippic orations. In a Shakespeare play, this man\ndeclares that Brutus “was the noblest Roman of them all.” This member of the Second\nTriumvirate had his forces defeated at the Battle of Actium [ACT-ee-um] during a Civil War\nagainst Octavian [ock-TAY-vee-uhn]. For 10 points, name this friend of Julius Caesar and lover\nof Cleopatra.",
      "answer": [
        "Mark Antony",
        "Antony",
        "Marcus Antonius",
        "Antonius"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler defeated the Shardana pirates and captured the vassal state of Amurru and the port of Sumur before his campaign against Muwatalli II. This man commissioned his mortuary temple in Thebes and a pair of temples that were relocated in 1968 to accommodate the Aswan High Dam. This husband of Nefertari won the battle of Kadesh against the Hittites, the opponent of his father, Seti I. For 10 points, name this long-ruling New Kingdom Egyptian pharaoh who built Abu Simbel.",
      "answer": "Ramesses the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "Jamshid [Jum-SHEED] could perform this action using a cup filled with an elixir of immortality. Methods of doing this in Babylonia made use of texts like Enuma Anu Enlil [Ehn- U-muh AH-nu EN-leel] and entailed the practice of haruspicy [har-OO-spih-see]. This action was performed by priests of Zeus at Dodona [duh-DO-nuh]. This action was performed by augurs in Rome and could involve watching birds or reading the entrails of sheep. For 10 points, name this action that involved determining omens or predicting the future.",
      "answer": "divination"
    },
    {
      "question": "According to one source, this person died fighting against the Massagetae [MASS-uh-gee- tay], led by Tomyris [Toe-my-ris], who put his head in a jar. This person won the battles of Pteria [tuh-REE-uh] and Thymbra against a rival ruler. This person’s cylinder is considered by some the oldest declaration of human rights. This son of Persis overthrew his grandfather Astyages, rebelling against the Medes [mee-dees]. He was both preceded and succeeded by rulers named Cambyses. For 10 points, name this founder of the Persian Empire.",
      "answer": "Cyrus the Great"
    },
    {
      "question": "Prior to his career as a politician, this man owned a firefighting business notorious for letting properties burn down so that this man could buy the land. He punished Mummius during the Third Servile War by renewing the practice of decimation. After the Battle of Carrhae, the Parthians killed this man by pouring molten gold down his throat. For ten points, name this legendarily rich Roman leader, a member of the First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey the Great.",
      "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Sicilian Vespers helped prevent one of these events from occurring by burning the ships of Charles of Anjou in Messina harbor. The use of Greek Fire in the Bosphorus strait helped stop one of these events. A successful one of these events saw Orban design the massive Dardanelles cannon at the behest of Mehmed II. One of the most well known of these events was ordered by Enrico Dandolo during the Fourth Crusade. For ten points, name these events that involve looting the capitol of the Byzantine Empire.",
      "answer": "sacks of Constantinople"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire won a battle by using hit-and-run tactics, then feigning retreat to lure Kitbuqa’s army into a trap; in that battle, this empire was led by Baibars and Saif ad-Din Qutuz. Shortly after Hulagu sacked Aleppo, this empire won the aforementioned Battle of Ain Jalut and retook Syria from the Mongols. These people created a sultanate centered in Cairo after ending the Ayyubid Dynasty. For ten points, name this class of Islamic soldiers in Egypt that originated from Turkish slaves.",
      "answer": "Mamluk sultanate"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire was ruled under the Kouroukan Fouga constitution, which established the Gbara legislature. A victory at the Battle of Kirina solidified this empire’s rule over the Sosso leader Sumanguru. Chihab al-Umari documented the travels of one ruler of this empire, who supposedly built a mosque every Friday on his hajj to Mecca. For ten points, name this West African empire that was founded by Sundiata Keita and led in the 14th century by Mansa Musa.",
      "answer": "Mali Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Indestructibles were a pair of stars considered only accessible by these figures. The action of raising the djed [jed] was performed to honor them at a celebration sometimes called the Feast of the Tail. That event, the Heb Sed, allowed one of these figures to establish the Amarna heresy. They were the pre-eminent preservers of the fundamental order of the universe, a concept known as Maat. One of these people mandated worship of a sun-disk known as Aten, and concurrently changed his own name to Akhenaten. For ten points, name these semi-divine rulers of ancient Egypt.",
      "answer": "ancient Egyptian pharaohs"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was deposed after losing at Flarchheim to Rudolph of Swabia. As a child, this man was targeted in the Kaiserswerth plot that left Anno II as regent. This man prompted a conflict by installing Guibert of Ravenna as Antipope Clement III. This man walked to Canossa Castle barefoot to beg forgiveness from Gregory VII after a dispute involving the pope’s authority to appoint bishops. For ten points, name this Holy Roman Emperor embroiled in the Lay Investiture controversy.",
      "answer": "Henry IV, Holy Roman Emperor or Heinrich IV"
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker’s concept of the “efficient cause” in the natural world was continued by his successor, Theophrastus. A graded scale of perfection established by this man to classify living organisms is known as his “Great Chain of Being.” This philosopher, who was exiled by Eurymedon the Hierophant, was accused by Hagnothemis of poisoning his most famous pupil, Alexander the Great. For ten points, name this Ancient Greek founder of the Lyceum and student of Plato.",
      "answer": "Aristotle"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man built a gigantic bridge over the Bay of Baiae to prove to a soothsayer he could ride a horse over the bay. This man’s predecssor was smothered by the Praetorian Prefect Macro. This emperor ordered an invasion of Britain that ended with his men collecting sea shells instead. Suetonius claimed that this man planned to make his horse Incitatus consul. The nickname “Little Soldier’s Boot” was given to, for ten points, what insane Roman emperor?",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus",
        "do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A primary source about life in this empire is provided by the letters of Lady Mary Wortley Montagu. The murdered miniaturist Elegant Effendi works under this empire in Orhan Pamuk’s novel My Name is Red. Cervantes’s left hand was badly maimed while fighting against this empire as part of the Spanish contingent at the Battle of Lepanto. For ten points, name this empire where authors were patronized by nobles in 19th century Bursa and Istanbul.",
      "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
    },
    {
      "question": "While serving as consul, a man of this name oversaw the debate over the Oppian Law restricting the amount of wealth a woman could own, as well as two Porcian Laws protecting citizens from severe punishment. A man with this name opposed Julius Caesar and once forced him to choose a consulship over a triumph. The elder statesman of this name got his wish in the Third Punic War when Scipio Africanus razed a city that legendarily had salt sowed in its soil. For ten points, give this name shared by a censor of Rome who repeated at the end of his speeches, “Carthage must be destroyed.”",
      "answer": [
        "Cato",
        "Cato the Younger",
        "Cato the Elder"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Scenes of this people’s daily life and armed conflict are among subject matter of paintings found in the Franc¸ois tomb. Cosimo de Medici bought a famous bronze statue of made by these people depicting a chimera. The prevalence of horse figurines in the Villanovan culture suggests their importance to these people, who lived in cities like Tarquinia and Veii. Present-day Umbria and Tuscany was home to, for ten points, what Italian people who fought a series of wars with ancient Rome?",
      "answer": "Etruscans"
    },
    {
      "question": "Edward Larson wrote a history of this election year titled A Magnificent Catastrophe. William Freehling claims that the Three-Fifths clause was central to the incumbent’s loss in this election year, whose winner gave a diplomatic inaugural address in which he claimed “We are all Republicans, we are all Federalists.” A Federalist supported a rival in this election year by claiming he was “by far not so dangerous a man” as Aaron Burr. Alexander Hamilton played a crucial role in, for ten points, what election year in which Thomas Jefferson replaced John Adams as President?",
      "answer": "US Presidential election of 1800"
    },
    {
      "question": "In demonstrating that dead yeast cells produced sugar via these things, Eduard Buchner disputed Louis Pasteur’s view that living cells were needed for fermentation. In 2018, Frances Arnold won the Nobel Prize in Chemistry for her work in engineering these things. The presence of one of these things named rennet allowed ancient Egyptians who stored milk in dried stomachs to create cheese. The suffix ase [spell it] is usually used in the names of, for ten points, what biological macromolecules that speed up chemical reactions?",
      "answer": "enzymes"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was assassinated by Cassius Chaeraea after attempting to permanently move to Alexandria. This man may have gone mad after the death of Julia Drusilla, leading to rumors that he appointed Incitatus as a state official. This son of Germanicus was affectionately called “little boot” by the legions. Tiberius was succeeded as emperor by, for ten points, what Roman emperor who supposedly made his horse a consul?",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Caesar",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus",
        "do not"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Akingofthislocationwasbelievedtohaveinventedthechariottohidehisserpentinefeet.Ericthonius ruled this location, as did another serpent-legged king named Cecrops, who judged an olive tree to be better than a salt water spring. Another king of this city died when his son returned with black sails on his boat after slaying the Minotaur. The mythological figures Theseus and Aegeus ruled, for ten points, what ancient Greek city whose origin myth includes Poseidon losing a contest to be its namesake?",
      "answer": [
        "Athens",
        "Attica before “city” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "After putting down Quintus Cassius Longinus’s rebellion in Spain, this man received a triumph and was Master of the Horse twice under Julius Caesar. This man, who served as the last pontifex maximus of the Roman Republic after Caesar’s death, was overthrown after trying to claim Sicily after the final defeat of Sextus Pompey, setting the stage for the final showdown between Antony and Octavian. For ten points, name this third member of the Second Triumvirate.",
      "answer": "Marcus Aemilius Lepidus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler debated Otanes and Megazubus over different governmental systems until he was chosen to be king because his slave Oebares made his horse neigh first at sunrise. This ruler overthrew Bardiya, who was possibly impersonated by Gaumata. Nebuchadnezzar III fought a ruler of this name, who created the first satrapies from a tax system inherited by Cyrus the Great. The Behistun Inscription was created by, for ten points, what ruler who led the first Persian invasion of Greece?",
      "answer": [
        "Darius the Great",
        "Darius I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s uncle of the same name and his brother Stesagoras each ruled the Chersonese as tyrants. Late in life, this man suffered a leg wound while attacking the island of Paros; he was imprisoned for treason and died of gangrene. This man, who was forced to fight the Scythians under Darius, convinced Athens to execute messengers sent by Darius demanding earth and water. The polemarch Callimachus broke a tie on the advice of this man, leading to a decisive victory in 490 BC. For ten points, name this general whose strategy won the Battle of Marathon.",
      "answer": "Miltiades the Younger"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of this ruler’s generals won the Battle of Mons Graupius, but that general was dismissed from office, contributingto theRoman historianTacitus’shatred ofthis ruler.This mancame topower afterthe short reign of his brother, and he was used as the archetype for despotic rule by later Roman historians. Agricola served, for ten points, what Roman Emperor, the second son of Vespasian and the last Flavian ruler?",
      "answer": "Titus Flavius Caesar Domitianus Augustus"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this civilization, the high priest was required to resign upon the death of his wife, who was responsible for the Argei rituals. A woman in this civilization was said to have dragged a statue of Cybele through a sandbar. This civilization operated a temple whose gates were closed during times of peace and opened during war. The two faced god Janus, Minerva, and Vulcan were worshiped in, for ten points, what civilization whose chief god was Jupiter?",
      "answer": [
        "ancient Rome",
        "Roman Empire and/or Roman Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The annexation of what is now this state was facilitated under the Newlands Resolution during the William McKinley administration. This state was formerly a Republic which was led by Sanford Dole. Sugarcane planters overthrew this modern day state’s native ruler, Queen Liliʻuokalani [[lee-lee-woh-kah-LUH-nee]]. For ten points, name this state in which an attack on a base which included Battleship Row served as a precursor to U.S. entry into World War Two.",
      "answer": [
        "Hawai'i",
        "Kingdom of Hawai'i",
        "Republic of Hawai'i",
        "Territory of Hawai'i"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required. A coalition led by these two cities lost to the strategos Epaminondas [[ee-pam-ih-NON-dahs]] at the Battle of Mantinea under the leadership of a king of the Eurypontid dynasty. One of these cities tore down the other’s “Long Wall” which reached Piraeus [[pie-RAY-us]], and these two states signed the \"fifty year\" Peace of Nicias. Admiral Lysander from one of these cities sank the other city’s Delian fleet during the Battle of Aegospotami [[ay-goh-SPOH-tah-mai]]. For ten points, name these two Greek poleis [[POH-lice]] which fought each other in the Peloponnesian War.",
      "answer": [
        "Athens and Sparta",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The most easterly of these cities, known as eskhata, was founded in the Fergana Valley as a way to maintain contact with the Sogdians. Another of these cities, partially named for a horse, served as a settlement for Iranian and Greek veterans. Another city with this name was the site of the Pharos which was built by the Ptolemies. For ten points, give this shared name of twenty cities founded by Alexander the Great, the most notable containing an extensive library.",
      "answer": "Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "question": "This structure uses two standards, A and B, for offsets. Coel Hen [[COIL HEN]], the legendary father of Saint Helena, used some buildings on this structure. John Clayton helped preserve this structure which parallels the Stanegate Road. A path following this structure passes a fort at Housesteads. This structure included an earthwork called the Vallum, and it was guarded by Milecastles. Located on the border of the Roman Empire and similar to the Antonine, for ten points, what is this fortification across Scotland?",
      "answer": "Hadrian's Wall"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this decade, Derek Jacobi portrayed a stuttering Roman emperor in the miniseries I, Claudius. Quincy Jones scored a smash-hit ABC miniseries in this decade based on a book about Alex Haley’s ancestry titled Roots. Sixteen Emmy Award nominations were given, with only one winner for Costume Design, to a TV show based in and named for this decade. For ten points, in what decade did the first two Godfather films win Academy Awards for Best Picture?",
      "answer": "1970s 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
    },
    {
      "question": "Music played by lunera [[loo-NEH-rah]] accompanied these people at some events before which these participants were usually massaged with oil. The greatest honor that these people could achieve was receiving a wooden sword known as a Rudis. The Hoplomachus [[hop-loh-MAHK-us]] and Murmillo [[muhr-MIH-loh]] were two specific types of these people who were trained at schools after being bought by a master. Including Spartacus and many rebels in the Third Servile War, for ten points, who were these enslaved competitive fighters of ancient Rome?",
      "answer": "Gladiators"
    },
    {
      "question": "Until the formation of this government, Eugene Leviné [[yoo-ZHEN leh-vee-NEH]] led a short-lived Soviet Republic in a southern state of this government's country. Polish Marxist Rosa Luxemburg co-led the Spartacus League against this government, leading to her execution by the Freikorps [[FRAI-kohr]]. Hyperinflation caused by this government occurred in part because of their need to pay reparations to the Allies, per the Treaty of Versailles. For ten points, name this German government which collapsed during the rise of Adolf Hitler.",
      "answer": [
        "Weimar Republic or German Reich",
        "Weimar government"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "To create votives of this substance, the Ancient Greeks used the Sphyrelaton, or the \"Hammer Elongated\" method. Despite being known as the \"Iron Man of India,\" Vallabhbhai Patel is depicted using this substance in the tallest statue on Earth, the Statue of Unity. Rodin [[roh-DAHN]] faced false accusations that he used a real person as the mold for his lifelike sculpture, The Age of [this metal]. The Little Mermaid in Copenhagen and The Thinker are cast in, for ten points, which historically valued metal alloy composed of Copper and Tin?",
      "answer": [
        "Bronze",
        "Age of Bronze"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The geographer Strabo uses this ruler's name to refer to a region in the Armenian highlands and Caucasian Albania. According to Herodotus, this ruler's 50,000-strong army disappeared in a desert sandstorm en route to destroy the Siwa Oasis. Shortly after his death by a self-inflicted stab wound, a civil war between the usurper Bardiya and the future Darius the Great broke out. The conquest of Egypt was completed by, for ten points, which Persian ruler and son of Cyrus the Great?",
      "answer": [
        "Cambyses II",
        "Cambysene"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to Herodotus [heh-ROD-uh-tuss], the earliest usage of these things occurred under the rule of Alyattes [ahl-YAH-tees] in Lydia, where they were made with electrum. The solidus was one of these items whose usage was introduced by Diocletian [dye-oh-CLEE-shun]. The field of numismatics studies these objects, which in the Roman Empire included asses, sestertii [sess-TER-shee], and denarii. For 10 points, identify these typically round, metal objects used as currency.",
        "answer": "coins"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which legendarily wealthy king of Lydia, who supposedly issued the first pure gold coins, was defeated by Cyrus the Great?",
        "answer": "Croesus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Coalition forces in this war bombed Highway 80 into the so-called Highway of Death. This war is the namesake of a “syndrome” that some have linked to sarin gas. This war was launched in response to an invasion of Kuwait the previous year. For 10 points, name this 1990 to 1991 war that included Operations Desert Shield and Desert Storm in which a US- led coalition fought Saddam Hussein.",
        "answer": "the First Persian Gulf War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This American, nicknamed “Stormin’ Norman”, led coalition forces in the Persian Gulf War.",
        "answer": "H. Norman Schwarzkopf"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A \"monkey-eating\" type of this animal is native to the Philippines. Deforestation in South America threatens the habitat of a large \"harpy\" type of this bird. The Holy Roman Empire used a double-headed one to represent the church and the state. A blue depiction of this kind of animal was used as the emblem of the National Recovery Administration. For 10 points, name this bird, whose \"bald\" type is an American national symbol.",
        "answer": "eagles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A black double-eagle is shown on the flag of what country, which became the first officially atheist country in the world under the rule of Enver Hoxha [“ho-jah”]?",
        "answer": "Republic of Albania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Persian-dictated “King’s Peace” brought an end to one war named for this city, which the general Lucius Mummius sacked in 146 BC. Ships could be moved across the massive diolkos [dee-OL-kos] ramp constructed by this city’s tyrant Periander. This city named the third primary order of Greek architecture, along with the Doric and Ionic orders. For 10 points, name this Greek city located on a namesake isthmus in the Peloponnesus.",
        "answer": "Corinth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Like the regions of Thrace and Boeotia [bee-OH-shah], Corinth lends its name to a popular type of what military equipment?",
        "answer": "helmet"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One ruler of this name brought together the Ten Thousand under Xenophon to fight the broker of the Peace of Antalcidas, Artaxerxes II [art-ah-zerk-zees], his brother. An earlier ruler of this name was killed by the Massagetae [mass-ah-geh-tye] after he refused to marry Queen Tomyris. That ruler of this name disparaged Babylon’s Nabonidus in an inscription on a clay cylinder and was buried in Pasargadae [pass-ar-gah-dye]. For ten points, give this name of a “Great” ruler who founded the Achaemenid Dynasty in Persia.",
        "answer": "Cyrus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Peace of Antalcidas ended a war named for this Greek city-state, which lies on a namesake isthmus roughly halfway between Athens and Sparta.",
        "answer": "Corinth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hur helped this figure defeat the Amalekites by raising his arms. This man quelled a rebellion by striking a stone on Horeb to create a spring. He ordered the construction of the Tabernacle, and married Zipporah while he was exiled in Midian. He was the brother of Miriam and Aaron, with whom this former prince cast ten plagues on a Pharaoh who may have been Ramses II. The Torah was legendarily written by, for ten points, what Abrahamic religious figure who led the Israelites out of Egypt?",
        "answer": [
          "Moses or Moshe",
          "Musa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was Moses’ spiritual successor. He prayed for the sun to stand still in the sky during a battle with the Amorites.",
        "answer": "Joshua or Jehoshua"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Charles Kinsey, John Ames, and Thomas Gilpin created early American machines for continuous production of this good. Bryan Donkin built a prototype of the Fourdrinier machine, which creates this good via a “form, press, dry” method. A high lignin content in the pulp will weaken this good, so the kraft process is used to separate out the needed cellulose. The Han dynasty invented, for ten points, what material that replaced silk and parchment as a medium for writing?",
        "answer": "paper"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This material was used for writing, as well as rope and baskets, prior to the invention of paper. The Egyptian Book of the Dead was preserved on this material, as was a mathematical text named for Alexander Rhind.",
        "answer": [
          "papyrus",
          "Rhind papyrus"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The non-Quaker Society of Friends led an independence movement in this nation during the early 19th century. One of this country’s islands, known for its production of mastic, or chewing gum, was the site of a massacre depicted in a Eugene Delacroix [de-la-quah] painting. Lord Byron died in the siege of Missolonghi during this nation’s war for independence, led by Alexander Ypsilantis against the Ottomans. For ten points, name this Balkan nation, the birthplace of Western democracy, where Ottoman forces stored munitions in the Parthenon.",
        "answer": "Greece"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Delacroix’s painting depicts the desolation after the Massacre at this Greek island.",
        "answer": "Chios"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Akrotiri was destroyed by one of these events near what is now Cape Kolumbo. The ROTAS-SATOR and ROMA-MILO magic squares were discovered in the ruins of another of these events, from which Rectina was to be rescued from Stabiae by a fast ship commanded by Pliny the Elder. For ten points, name these devastating events that took place on Santorini circa 1500 BC, wiping out the Minoans, and on Vesuvius in 79 AD, destroying the town of Pompeii.",
        "answer": [
          "volcanic eruptions",
          "descriptions of volcanoes"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A pyroclastic flow from Vesuvius destroyed this town southwest of the volcano, as opposed to Pompeii and Oplontis to the south and east. Its high standard of living is evident through the marble ruins it left behind.",
        "answer": "Herculaneum"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This civilization developed the “false position” method to solve systems of linear equations. This civilization’s YBC 7289 tablet contains a crude estimation for the square root of 2, while another tablet of 15 Pythagorean triples is this civilization’s Plimpton 322. In 2016, it was announced that this civilization understood the trapezoid method from elementary calculus. Much of this civilization’s scientific accomplishments were taken to the west after a 331 B.C. defeat at Susa by Alexander the Great. For ten points, name this ancient Mesopotamian civilization that used a base 60 counting system.",
        "answer": [
          "Babylonia",
          "Babylonian empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "An early physical representation for this mathematical concept was first conceived during the Seleucid period of Babylon. This concept was represented by spaces using Chinese counting rods.",
        "answer": "zero"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire faced the Alid revolt of Mohammed the Pure Soul, and a century later, the slaves of Basra rose up against this empire in the Zanj rebellion. One ruler of this dynasty sent a chess set and water clock to Charlemagne and built a House of Wisdom that was destroyed in Hulagu Khan’s 1258 siege of its capital, Baghdad. Avicenna and al-Khwarizmi worked during, for ten points, what third Islamic caliphate, the successors of the Umayyads?",
        "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Joyce’s Ulysses, Stephen Daedalus dreams of this aforementioned ruler, the builder of the House of Wisdom.",
        "answer": "Harun al-Rashid"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Twenty-two baboons line the upper frieze of the larger of two structures in this complex, which was rediscovered by Jean-Louis Burckhardt and Giovanni Belzoni. The inner walls of this pair of structures align with the sun in February and October, illuminating statues of Ptah, Ra-Horakhty, Amun, and the pharaoh who constructed these temples. This portion of the Nubian Monuments was moved to protect it from flooding caused by the Aswan High Dam. For ten points, name this pair of Egyptian temples fronted by massive statues of Nefertari and Ramses II.",
        "answer": "Abu Simbel"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Temple of Nefertari at Abu Simbel is dedicated to the queen and this cow-headed Egyptian goddess of motherhood.",
        "answer": "Hathor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was ruled by an Amorite dynasty until a sack by the Hittites and an occupation by the Kassites. This empire rivaled, then allied with, the Medians to their north. This empire was refounded after the death of the powerful Assyrian king Ashurbanipal. A law code that governed this empire contained the principle of “an eye for an eye,” and its capital city legendarily featured intricate hanging gardens. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian empire ruled by Hammurabi.",
        "answer": "Babylonian Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Hanging Gardens were built by the second Babylonian king of this name; he also destroyed Solomon’s Temple in Jerusalem and began the Babylonian Captivity.",
        "answer": "Nebuchadnezzar II or Nebuchadrezzar II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man constructed, and named for himself, a fortified road along the Arabian border. The Edict on Maximum Prices was this ruler’s attempt to combat inflation by replacing the debased denarius. He appointed his valuable ally, the general Maximian, as co-ruler with Galerius and Chlorus as junior rulers. This man’s ascension ended the Crisis of the Third Century and, he ordered the last major persecution of Christians in his empire. For ten points, name this Roman Emperor whose tetrarchy split the empire into four sections.",
        "answer": "Diocletian or Diocles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Diocletian reduced the size of this bodyguard of Roman emperors, although he did keep their prefect as an important official in his empire. They were eventually abolished by Constantine.",
        "answer": "Praetorian Guard"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man replaced his superior, Quintus Caecilius Metellus, as the commander of the expedition against Jugurtha. He decisively defeated the Cimbri and the Teutones while serving as consul, a position that he was elected to seven times. In an effort to minimize the baggage train, this man ordered his soldiers to carry their supplies on his back, earning them the nickname of this man’s mules. For ten points, name this Roman general, the first to recruit soldiers from the poor, one of his many military reforms.",
        "answer": "Gaius Marius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marius’s rival late in life was this man, the first general to march on Rome. He instituted proscription to target his political enemies.",
        "answer": "Lucius Cornelius Sulla Felix"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This activity, when conducted in a morally incorrect way, was condemned as “nefas” by the Ancient Romans. Augustine used Romans 13:4 to support this activity when conducted by the church. The School of Salamanca attempted to develop a theory of this activity based on Thomas Aquinas’ three conditions for its justification. The rights of jus in bello and jus ad bellum both involve this activity. For ten points, name this general term for an armed conflict between societies.",
        "answer": "war"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to numerous religious discussions on war, this Prussian military theorist described war as the “continuation of politics by other means” in his secular treatise On War.",
        "answer": "Carl von Clausewitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these provinces boasted the largest Roman baths outside of Rome after Constantine renovated Augusta Treverorum. Imperial Roman influence in these provinces began when Domitius Ahenobarbus was summoned to aid the city of Massilia. This region, which was divided into the provinces of Belgica, Aquitania, and Celtica, was conquered when a circumvallation wall helped defeat the Averni tribe at Alesia. Julius Caesar conquered, for ten points, what ancient region in modern-day France?",
        "answer": [
          "provinces of Gaul or Gallia",
          "Gallia Belgica",
          "Gallia Narbonensis after “Domitius” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Gallic Pont du Gard was an example of what type of Roman structure that serviced Nimes [neem]?",
        "answer": "aqueducts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was plunged into a series of civil wars after the assassinations of Berdibek and Janibeg, and it was dissolved after Akhmat backed down against troops from former vassal kingdoms at a standoff at the Ugra River. This empire’s power diminished after Dmitri Donskoy liberated Moscow at the Battle of Kulikovo. The cities of Old and New Sarai were capitals of, for ten points, what kingdom that stretched into Western Europe, a Mongol horde named for the color of its tents?",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Horde",
          "Kipchak Khanate"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "At the Battle of Legnica [leh-neetz-ah], the Golden Horde infamously filled nine sacks with these body parts after removing them from their Polish prisoners.",
        "answer": "ears"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event began when Lucius Cimber presented a petition to return his brother from exile. Security forces failed to reach this event in time, even though Servilius Casca had leaked its details. This event triggered the Liberator’s Civil War, in which the perpetrator Cassius was hunted down by the Second Triumvirate. Outside the Theater of Pompey, this event’s target may have cried “et tu, Brute?” [broo-tay] as he was stabbed. For ten points, name this 44 BC event in which a dictator of Rome was killed.",
        "answer": "assassination or murder, stabbing, etc. of Julius Caesar"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Caesar’s death was avenged at this 42 BC battle in Macedonia, where an alliance of Marc Antony and Octavian compelled the defeated Brutus to commit suicide.",
        "answer": "Battle of Philippi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jews living under this empire were recruited into cantonist schools and forced to complete years of military service. Menahim Beilis was accused by this empire’s officials of murdering a young boy and dumping his body near a brick factory, as related in Bernard Malamud’s novel The Fixer. The Pale of Settlement was created to house Jews by a female ruler of this empire. For ten points, name this empire which allowed some Jews to serve on the Duma under Nicholas II.",
        "answer": "Russian Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pale of Settlement on Russia’s western frontier included all of this modern Baltic state, where over 100,000 people were killed by the Nazis in Ponary Forest near Vilnius.",
        "answer": "Lithuania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the Aeneid, a god of this domain was the father of Circe, the mother of Latinus. A Roman emperor who worshiped a god of this domain controversially took the Vestal Virgin Aquilia Severa as his fourth wife; that emperor, who gave his name to a deity of this domain, was Elagabalus. A cult centered around an “unconquered” deity of this domain was popular in the Roman Empire until the 4th century. For ten points, give this domain of the deities Sol Invictus and Helios.",
        "answer": [
          "sun",
          "Sol before read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 3rd century Roman emperor ended the breakaway Gallic and Palmyrene Empires, built a series of walls in Rome, and established Sol Invictus as one of the chief deities of the Roman pantheon.",
        "answer": "Aurelian or Lucius Domitius Aurelianus Augustus, but do not"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man befriended the Vestal Virgin Licinia to take her land. This man died in a skirmish after his assistant Octavius awkwardly tried to stop him from taking part in a peace negotiation. This man became wealthy by running a bucket brigade that would not help douse fires until homeowners paid him. This man’s victory at the Battle of the Siler River ended a slave revolt. A Parthian army killed this man and legendarily poured molten gold in the mouth of his corpse. For ten points, name this wealthy Roman who put down Spartacus’ revolt and formed the First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey.",
        "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After Spartacus’ revolt was put down, Crassus ordered the crucifixion of six thousand slaves along this road from Rome to Brindisium.",
        "answer": "Appian Way or Via Appia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire came to power after throwing off the yoke of the Kaniaga kingdom of the Sosso peoples. This empire appointed farbins to rule over conquered lands and referred to its territories as the “Twelve Doors.” This empire’s victory at the 13th century Battle of Kirina over Sumanguru allowed this empire to rule much of Africa. Sankore University became a madrassa under, for ten points, what west African empire that was eventually supplanted by the Songhai and once ruled by Mansa Musa?",
        "answer": "Mali Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This “Lion of Mali” won the Battle of Kirina, founded the Mali Empire, and was an older relative of Mansa Musa.",
        "answer": [
          "Mansa Sundiata Keita",
          "either",
          "both"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man briefly retired to Caprera, an island he partially owned, after he was wounded and captured at the Battle of Aspromonte. This former schoolmaster worked for the Republic of Rio Grande do Sul in his early career, granting him the nickname “hero of two worlds.” This man was victorious at the Battle of the Volturnus, which came near the end of his Expedition of the Thousand. For ten points, name this commander of the Redshirts, a hero of Italian unification.",
        "answer": "Giuseppe Garibaldi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Expedition of the Thousand ended in February 1861 at the Siege of Gaeta, where this king surrendered, ending the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies. The last Holy Roman Emperor shares this king’s name and number.",
        "answer": "Francis II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Douglas Hofstadter’s massive work Le Ton Beau de Marot is a set of reflections on this activity. Walter Benjamin wrote an essay titled for the “Task” of someone who performs this activity. When doing this action, one sometimes must choose whether to prioritize literal or stylistic accuracy. The discovery of the Rosetta Stone allowed this to be done with Egyptian sources for the first time. For ten points, name this process of rendering texts from one language into another.",
        "answer": [
          "translation",
          "word forms",
          "translating poetry, based on the first clue"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Max Muller was a prominent translator of works in this ancient language, whose shared roots with Latin and Greek were the first suggestion of the Indo-European language family.",
        "answer": "Sanskrit"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man helped reinstate Phocis as the Oracle of Delphi during the Second Sacred War. This man faced a revolt in Miletus, which partly caused this lover of Aspasia to transfer funds from the treasury of the Delian League to his city. Thucydides recorded a famous funeral oration given by this man during the first year of a lengthy war against Sparta. For ten points, name this statesman who led during the Golden Age of Athens and the start of the Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Pericles BONUS:AccordingtothisGreekcomicplaywright’sThe Archanians,Pericles’consortAspasiasupposedly convinced him to issue the Megarian Decree. This author’s anti-war plays include Lysistrata. ANSWER: Aristophanes 8 In this year, Patrick Dunn helped organize a demonstration in Tompkins Square that police brutally repressed. The collapse of Jay Cooke & Company, which was unable to sell enough bonds in Northern Pacific Railway, helped trigger a financial crisis in this year, as did the passage of a Coinage Act that became known as the “Crime of” this year. For ten points, name this year in which an economic panic struck the US during the Grant administration. ANSWER: 1873"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This senator from Ohio introduced the Coinage Act of 1873 and served as treasury secretary under Rutherford B. Hayes.",
        "answer": "John Sherman"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler of this empire ordered Ketevan the Martyr’s execution after she refused to renounce Christianity. Although the Shirley brothers helped modernize this empire’s army, its troops suffered a defeat against the Hotaki Empire at the Battle of Gulnabad. They’re not Bulgars, but after this dynasty won the Battle of Merv, its first ruler had his enemy’s skull fashioned into a drinking goblet. That man’s son, Tahmasp I, signed the Peace of Amasya with a rival empire that won the Battle of Chaldiran under the leadership of Selim the Grim. Ismail I founded, for ten points, what Iranian dynasty that practiced Shia Islam?",
        "answer": "Safavid Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Safavid shah, who diminished the power of the Qizilbash, moved the Safavid capital to Isfahan. He allied with the English East India Company to retake Hormuz from the Portuguese.",
        "answer": "Abbas I or Abbas the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A legend relates that these people came into existence after a namesake region revolted against Agis I. People born of these women were labeled as nothoi. An earthquake in the Eurotas Valley allowed these people to launch a revolt. Members of the Krypteia could kill these people without repercussions. These subjugated farmers made up the bulk of the population of ancient Laconia. For ten points, name this class of slaves in Sparta.",
        "answer": "helots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Most helots worked as farmers, but some worked as servants in this education system for Spartan boys.",
        "answer": "agoge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire used the paiza seal to indicate officials authorized to use the stations of the Yam supply route. This empire conquered the Kingdom of Dali and installed a local governor known as a Tusi [tu-szu]. This empire was betrayed by its vassal, the Western Xia, and it finished one conquest at the Battle of Yamen on the Pearl River Delta. After crossing the Yangtze, this empire was able to defeat the Southern Song Dynasty. For ten points, name this empire that conquered China under the rule of Genghis and Kublai Khan.",
        "answer": "Mongol Empire"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In Russia, the Yam system survived the fall of this khanate, an offshoot of the Mongol Empire that was founded by Batu Khan in 1242.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Horde",
          "Ulug Ulus",
          "Kipchak Khanate",
          "Ulus of Jochi"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An Adele Berlin article about “[this book] and Ancient Storytelling” argues that it was meant to be a historical novella. Herodotus’ description of the domineering Amestris is associated by some scholars with this book’s character of Vashti, who is ousted as queen for refusing to appear at a banquet. King Ahasuerus is saved by Mordecai and the plot of Haman is thwarted in, for ten points, what book of the Old Testament, named for a queen of Persia, that depicts the origins of Purim?",
        "answer": "Book of Esther"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Ahasuerus is most frequently identified with this Persian ruler, who ruled from 486 to 465 BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Xerxes the Great",
          "Xerxes I"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler deposed his client king, Cotys I of the Bosporan kingdom, in favor of annexing the Crimean Peninsula. This emperor used a collapsible boat in an attempt to kill his mother; when that failed, he killed her with an assassin. This ruler committed suicide in 68 AD after it was clear Galba would take over. For ten points, name this adopted son of Claudius, a Roman emperor who legendarily fiddled while Rome burned.",
        "answer": "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This mother of Nero and sister of Caligula married Claudius in 49 AD as a power play; she very probably poisoned Claudius four years later to ensure Nero would become emperor.",
        "answer": "Agrippina the Younger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was called the \"patient in a cast\" during the Aprillian government. The slogan \"Allag,\" or \"Change,\" was used by this country's PASOK party, which was brought down by the 1989 Koskotas [[kohs-KOH-tahs]] financial scandal. Students in this country cried \"Bread-Education-Liberty!\" during a 1973 strike targeting its Regime of the Colonels whose reign coincided with that of Constantine II. For ten points, name this country on the Aegean Sea, the site of the Athens Polytechnic uprising.",
        "answer": [
          "Greece or Hellenic Republic",
          "or Hellas"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Constantine II was the last king of Greece and the son of this ruler, who served from 1947 to 1964 and shared his name with a Biblical apostle.",
        "answer": "Paul of Greece 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "George Reisner [[RYE-snur]] abandoned excavation of these places due to flooding which collapsed tunnels and killed his crew. Giuseppe Ferlini destroyed several of these places while searching for treasure in Meroë [[MEH-row-ee]]. According to legend, one of the first examples of these places was designed by Imhotep for Djoser [[JOH-ser]]. The largest example of these places was built for Khufu. For ten points, name these massive tombs, whose \"Great\" examples are located in Giza, Egypt.",
        "answer": "Pyramid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pyramids of Meroë [[MEH-row-ee]] were built by this ancient Sudanese kingdom, which was known as Nubia by ancient Egyptians.",
        "answer": [
          "Kush",
          "Kushites"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The founder of this dynasty, Rudolf, is seen sitting at the gates of purgatory in Dante’s Divine Comedy. A member of this family named Ferdinand I fought many “Little Wars” with the Ottoman Empire after turning back Suleiman the Magnificent's 1529 siege of this family’s capital. Charles VI of this dynasty secured the passage of the Pragmatic Sanction, allowing his daughter Maria Theresa to take the throne. For ten points, name this Austrian dynasty which held the title Holy Roman Emperor for three centuries.",
        "answer": [
          "House of Habsburg or Habsburgs",
          "Hapsburgs"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Due to inbreeding, many members of the House of Habsburg had what enlarged facial feature?",
        "answer": [
          "Habsburg Jaw or Habsburg lip",
          "Habsburg chin",
          "or Austrian lip",
          "descriptive answers indicating a large lower jaw, chin,",
          "lip"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Successful commanders from this kingdom were often equated to the god Montu, a war deity who takes the shape of a bull. This polity employed the Medjay, a distinct Cushitic speaking people who served as a paramilitary police force. This kingdom created the sickle shaped sword meant for close-combat known as the Khopesh, and its military mass-adopted the chariot after being invaded by the Hyksos [[HIK-sohs]]. For ten points, name this ancient African kingdom which fought at the Battles of Megiddo and the Nile Delta.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Egypt",
          "Aegypttos",
          "Kemet"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The invading Hyksos were likely from what Levantine region? The Biblical Promised Land corresponds to this region, which included Philistia and Phoenicia.",
        "answer": [
          "Canaan",
          "Kenaʿn",
          "Canaanites"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A tyrant of this city named Dionysius the Elder arrested the philosopher Plato and sold him into slavery following a disagreement. A former general of Pyrrhus of Epirus, Hiero II, served as a tyrant of this city, becoming a client of Rome during the First Punic War. Archimedes allegedly used a parabolic reflector to defend this city from a Roman attack, inventing the first \"heat ray.\" For ten points, name this ancient Greek colony in the southeast of Sicily.",
        "answer": [
          "Syracuse",
          "Syracusa",
          "or Sarausa",
          "or Syracusae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first settlers to Syracuse were from which Greek city-state which shares its name with an isthmus that connects Attica and the Peloponnese?",
        "answer": "Corinth or Korinthos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"phantom time hypothesis\" claims that in this century, Pope Sylvester II and Otto III made up three centuries of European history to legitimize Otto's claim to the Holy Roman Empire. In this century, Callinicus [[kah-lee-NYE-kuss]] of Heliopolis created the incendiary \"Greek Fire\" weapon. Byzantine Emperor Heraclius lost the possessions of Roman Syria and Egypt to the Rashidun Caliphate in this century. Islam emerged during, for ten points, what early medieval century?",
        "answer": [
          "Seventhth Century",
          "the 600s"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A Byzantine emperor of this name persecuted the Manichaeans [[mah-neh-KAY- ans]] in the 7th century. A \"Great\" emperor of this name reconquered much of the Western Empire with help from his strategos, Belisarius.",
        "answer": [
          "Justinian",
          "Justinian I",
          "or Justinian II"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this modern-day country, a breakaway general who was fond of using a metaphor about plucking the tail off a horse held off Metellus Pius and Pompey for seven years. This present-day country was the location of Quintus Sertorius's attempt to rebel against Rome. Hannibal's attack on Saguntum in this present-day country began the Second Punic War. Hadrian and Trajan were both born in what is now this country. For ten points, name this country where Romans expanded cities such as Valentia, Corduba, and Toletum, or modern Toledo.",
        "answer": [
          "Spain",
          "Kingdom of Spain",
          "or Reino de Espana",
          "Roman Hispania"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the division of Hispania Ulterior in 27 BC, the southwestern portion of Iberia comprised which province, the name of which was historically an alternate for Portugal?",
        "answer": "Hispana Lusitania"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A school of historiographical thought named for Columbia professor William Archibald Dunning was accused of taking \"white supremacist\" stances on this time period, leading to a direct refutation by W.E.B. Du Bois [[doo-BOYSS]] in his book Black [this era]. In one thesis, historian Erich Foner disputes that \"carpetbaggers\" and \"scalawags\" were the cause of the failure of this period. The military occupation of the rebelling Confederate States occurred during, for ten points, which period in the South in the 19th century?",
        "answer": [
          "Reconstruction",
          "Black Reconstruction"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Dunning School demonized a branch of the Republican party, which took on this alliterative moniker, for botching Reconstruction by advocating for civil rights?",
        "answer": "Radical Republicans"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The American company Hobby Lobby illegally purchased artifacts from this modern nation through dealers in the United Arab Emirates to populate their Museum of the Bible. Archeologist Gertrude Bell first excavated the Al-Ukhaidir [[ook-\"HIGH\"-deer]] Fortress in this nation, which was built by Caliph Isa ibn Musa to defend the Abbasid city of Karbala. The World Heritage site known as Ashur lies in, for ten points, which modern nation of the Middle East, governed from Baghdad?",
        "answer": "Republic of Iraq"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The city of Babylon contained an ancient \"Gate\" dedicated to which Mesopotamian goddess of love who attempts to woo Gilgamesh in an ancient epic?",
        "answer": [
          "Ishtar",
          "Ishtar Gate",
          "Inanna"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "It's not alchemists, but people of this profession were rounded up and killed by Louis XIV's officials during the Affair of the Poisons. It's not magicians, but escape-artist Harry Houdini undertook a campaign funded by the Scientific American to debunk these figures. The Pythia was a priestess of Apollo who specifically did this job. Pliny the Elder is the first historian to mention the use of a crystal ball used by magi in this position. The use of divination is done by, for ten points, what specific people who claim to prophesize the future?",
        "answer": [
          "Fortune-Tellers",
          "Psychics",
          "or Mediums",
          "or Oracles",
          "descriptions of people with precognition",
          "the ability to see the future"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Pythia served as the head of an Oracle in which Phocian city considered the center of the Earth by the Ancient Greeks?",
        "answer": [
          "Delphi",
          "Pytho"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The tide of a war on this continent was turned by Bocchus [[BOH-kus]] switching sides and betraying Jugurtha to Sulla. Cato the Younger killed himself on this continent, where Masinissa [[mahs-sih-NEES-uh]] united the kingdom of Numidia. Syphax [[SYE-fahx]] allied with Hasdrubal on this continent, where a decisive battle at Zama ended the Second Punic War. Scipio acquired an agnomen by defeating Hannibal on, for ten points, what continent, home to the city of Carthage and the Roman provinces of Mauretania and Egypt?",
        "answer": "Africa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Byzantine general and servant of Justinian reclaimed Ad Decimum and Tricamarum for the Eastern Roman Empire during a 530s war with the Vandal king Gelimer.",
        "answer": "Flavius Belisarius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An archaeologist who studied these people, Emil Forrer, suggests that their term \"Ahhiyawa\" [[ah-HEE-ywah]] refers to the Achaean [[ah-KAY-ehn]] Greeks, based on references in the 25,000 tablets found at Boğazköy [[BOHZ-koy]]. This people's prince Zannanza, who almost took the throne of Egypt, was the son of their expansionist emperor Šuppiluliuma [[soo-pih-loo-LYOO-mah]]. These people spoke the oldest known Indo- European language and fought with Ramses II at the Battle of Kadesh. For ten points, name this ancient Anatolian civilization whose final capital was Hattusa.",
        "answer": "Hittites"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prince Zannanza died on the way to marry the widow of this pharaoh, who reversed the monotheistic reforms of his father Akhenaten.",
        "answer": [
          "Tutankhamun",
          "King Tut"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A shepherd of this name raised the young Cyrus the Great after a steward of Astyages [[ah-STY-ah-gees]] was tasked with killing the child. A war with this name began after a king orchestrated the Asiatic Vespers, a genocide of Romans in Asia Minor. Pompey the Great defeated a king of this name in the Battle of the Lycus, forcing him to flee to Crimea and commit suicide. The Kingdom of Pontus was ruled by six rulers with, for ten points, which name of Persian origin, derived from that of a sun god?",
        "answer": [
          "Mithridates",
          "Mithridatic War",
          "Mithridates VI Eupator"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The first Mithridatic War occurred simultaneously to which period of domestic unrest caused by allied city-states agitating for Roman citizenship?",
        "answer": [
          "Social War",
          "Marsic War"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This candidate was dubiously endorsed by British ambassador Lionel Sackville- West in the Murchison Letter, which resulted in this man losing New York. Four years earlier, this man benefitted from another swing in Irish votes when Samuel Burchard denounced him as the candidate of \"rum, Romanism, and rebellion.\" This candidate defeated James G. Blaine before splitting two elections with Benjamin Harrison. For ten points, name this only Democratic president of the Gilded Age, who served two non- consecutive terms.",
        "answer": "Grover Cleveland or Stephen Grover Cleveland"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1884 election against Blaine, Cleveland also benefitted from the defection of this Republican faction led by Carl Schurz and Richard Henry Dana III that opposed corruption in the civil service system.",
        "answer": "Mugwumps"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Several red-haired mummies discovered in this desert are believed to have spoken the extinct Indo-European Tocharian languages. The Gushi culture likely constructed the trading city of Gaochang in this desert. The nomadic Buddhist Dzungar [[ZOON-gahr]] people traveled along the Tarim Basin in this desert and conducted trade in cities such as Kashgar. For ten points, name this desert which was a significant trading center for the Uyghur [[WEE-gur]] peoples.",
        "answer": [
          "Taklamakan Desert",
          "Teklimakan Desert"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Territory in the Tarim Basin was briefly ruled during the time of Kanishka the Great by what Bactrian empire that used Greek in its administration, practiced Buddhism, and controlled much of present-day Afghanistan, Pakistan, and northern India?",
        "answer": "Kushan Empire"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "ROMAN EMPERORS",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Possibly ordered his mother’s assassination and ruled during the Great Fire of Rome?",
          "answer": [
            "Nero",
            "Nero Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Maxentius [max-ENN-shuss] at the Battle of the Milvian [MILL-vee-uhn] Bridge\nand introduced Christianity to the Empire?",
          "answer": [
            "Constantine the Great",
            "Constantine",
            "Constantine I",
            "Saint Constantine",
            "Constantinius",
            "Flavius Valerius Aurelius Constantinus Augustus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known for his insanity and attempting to make his horse a Consul?",
          "answer": [
            "Caligula",
            "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the last of the Five Good Emperors and author of Meditations?",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus",
            "Marcus Aurelius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ended the Crisis of the Third Century and created the Tetrarchy?",
          "answer": [
            "Diocletian",
            "Gaius Aurelius Valerius Diocletianus Augustus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded his father Vespasian and was Emperor during the Vesuvius eruption?",
          "answer": [
            "Titus",
            "Titus Flavius Caesar Vespasianus Augustus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was captured in battle and made into a footstool by Sassanid King Shapur I?",
          "answer": [
            "Valerian",
            "Publius Licinius Valerianus Augustus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of the Frigidus [“frigid”-uss] and was the last to rule over the entire Empire?",
          "answer": [
            "Theodosius the Great",
            "Theodosius I",
            "Theodosius",
            "Flavius Theodosius Augustus"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Roman Emperor…"
    },
    {
      "category": "PELOPONNESIAN WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Century in which the conflict took place?",
          "answer": [
            "5th century BCE",
            "5TH BC",
            "5TH BCE",
            "400S BCE",
            "400S BC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of a contemporary history of the war?",
          "answer": "Thucydides"
        },
        {
          "question": "City whose namesake decree issued by Athens started the war?",
          "answer": "Megara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Athens in the first part of the war who gave a famous funeral oration?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island that was the target of a disastrous Athenian expedition led by Nicias [nih-see-us]?",
          "answer": [
            "Sicily",
            "Sicilia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of slaves in Sparta incited by Athens to revolt?",
          "answer": [
            "Helots",
            "Helotes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Sparta who won the battle of Aegospotami [ee-go-spot-uh-mee], the decisive battle\nof the war?",
          "answer": [
            "Lysander",
            "Lysandros"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of people that took power in Athens after the end of the war with the help of Sparta?",
          "answer": [
            "Thirty Tyrants",
            "Triakonta Tyrannoi"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the Peloponnesian War, who or what was the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "Enemies of Rome",
      "prompt": "Which person or group...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Led a Carthaginian army, including elephants, over the Alps during the Second Punic War?",
          "answer": "Hannibal Barca"
        },
        {
          "question": "Did not sack Rome when Pope Leo I convinced Attila to turn this group back?",
          "answer": "Huns"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a gladiator and slave revolt leader, whose followers were crucified along the Appian Way?",
          "answer": "Spartacus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were led by Vercingetorix but was defeated by Julius Caesar at Alesia in modern France?",
          "answer": "Gauls"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sacked Rome in 410 AD under their leader, Alaric?",
          "answer": "Visigoths"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led the Iceni against Suetonius in Britannia before her AD 60 death?",
          "answer": "Boudica or Boadicea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proclaimed “Woe to the vanquished” when he sacked Rome in 390 BC?",
          "answer": "Brennus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ambushed Quinctillius Varus and his former Roman allies in Teutoberg Forest, causing Augustus to shout “Give me back my legions!”",
          "answer": "Arminius or Hermann"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alcohol",
      "prompt": "In the history of alcohol, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "13-year period of American history when sale and transport of alcohol was banned by the 18th Amendment.",
          "answer": "Prohibition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that ended that ban.",
          "answer": "21st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Process by which a fermented beverage, like vodka or moonshine, is purified by selective evaporation?",
          "answer": [
            "distillation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of sparkling wine supposedly invented in France by the monk Dom Perignon?",
          "answer": "champagne"
        },
        {
          "question": "1791 rebellion in western Pennsylvania against Alexander Hamilton’s tax on spirits.",
          "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for an ancient Greek drinking party, which names and is depicted in a Platonic dialogue about the purpose of love.",
          "answer": "Symposium"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek wine whose flavor and name comes from the resin used to seal the bottle in ancient times.",
          "answer": "retsina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian officer killed in a drunken argument by Alexander the Great, whom he had saved at the Battle of the Granicus.",
          "answer": "Cleitus the Black"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Nazi Germany",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Four-armed symbol used to represent the Third Reich.",
          "answer": "swastika"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country invaded on September 1, 1939, triggering World War II.",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of Poland",
            "Second Polish Republic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Code name for the Nazi invasion of the Soviet Union, named for a leader of the Holy Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primarily-German speaking area of Czechoslovakia that was invaded and annexed in March 1939.",
          "answer": "Sudetenland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deputy Fuhrer who was captured in Scotland after trying to make peace with the United Kingdom.",
          "answer": "Rudolf Hess"
        },
        {
          "question": "SA leader accused of trying to overthrow Hitler, who was arrested and killed on July 1, 1934.",
          "answer": "Ernst Rohm"
        },
        {
          "question": "Unsuccessful 1944 plan to assassinate Hitler via a bomb at the Wolf’s Lair, orchestrated by Claus von Stauffenberg.",
          "answer": [
            "Operation Valkyrie",
            "July 20th plot"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anti-Hitler student group at the University of Munich, six members of which were executed in 1943 for distributing pamphlets.",
          "answer": "The White Rose"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Greek Politics",
      "prompt": "In the history of Greek politics, both ancient and modern, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern capital city, which ostracized potential tyrants during its ancient Golden Age.",
          "answer": "Athens"
        },
        {
          "question": "7th century BC lawmaker whose remarkably harsh law code inspired a common adjective.",
          "answer": [
            "Draco",
            "draconian and word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for intense spending cuts and tax increases imposed on Greece by the EU in return for a bailout.",
          "answer": [
            "austerity measures",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern right-wing, neo-Nazi party, which holds the third most seats in Greek parliament behind Syriza and New Democracy.",
          "answer": [
            "Golden Dawn or Chrysi Avgi",
            "XA",
            "chi alpha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of Syriza and current Prime Minister of Greece.",
          "answer": "Alexis Tsipras"
        },
        {
          "question": "So-called“firstcitizen”ofhiscity-state, whousedtheDelianLeague’streasurytobuildtheParthenon.",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Milesian immigrant and lover of the aforementioned “first citizen,” who may have run a brothel.",
          "answer": "Aspasia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Hill just west of the Acropolis, used by Cleisthenes to deliver political reforms to popular assemblies.",
          "answer": "Pnyx"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ramesses the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Ancient civilization whose New Kingdom rulers included Ramesses the Great.",
          "answer": "ancient Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Status that Ramesses aspired to achieve. Other beings with this status included Ra and Horus.",
          "answer": [
            "godhood",
            "broad equivalents relating to divinity"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Military vehicles that Ramesses used, consisting of a carriage pulled by horses.",
          "answer": "chariots"
        },
        {
          "question": "1274 BC battle that Ramesses fought against the Hittites, the largest battle of those vehicles in history.",
          "answer": "Battle of Kadesh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Diplomatic agreement made between Ramesses and Hattusili III, the first recorded example in history.",
          "answer": "peace treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Site of Ramesses’s tomb, located near Thebes. The tomb of Tutankhamun was also located here.",
          "answer": "Valley of the Kings"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Ramesses, for whom he constructed a temple at Abu Simbel.",
          "answer": "Nefertari"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region to the south, home to the kingdoms of Kush and Mero¨e, that Ramesses attacked.",
          "answer": "Nubia"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Justinian the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire that Justinian ruled, which grew out of the Eastern Roman Empire.",
          "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious official appointed by Justinian, the head of the Roman Catholic Church.",
          "answer": "pope or Bishop of Rome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Church built in Constantinople by Justinian. Converted to a mosque after the Ottoman conquest, it sits next to the Blue Mosque.",
          "answer": "Hagia Sophia"
        },
        {
          "question": "African city reconquered by Justinian from the Vandals, once the capital of Rome’s rival for the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "Carthage"
        },
        {
          "question": "Riots that nearly toppled Justinian after a series of chariot races got out of hand.",
          "answer": "Nika Riots"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region ruled by Justinian’s rival, the Sassanid Empire, from their cities in Ctesiphon [tess-ih-fon] and Esfahan.",
          "answer": [
            "Persia",
            "Parthia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Influential wife of Justinian, who rose from being an actress to Empress.",
          "answer": "Theodora"
        },
        {
          "question": "General employed by Justinian to conquer Italy, before his eventual disgrace and begging on the streets of Rome.",
          "answer": "Belisarius"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Pompey the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival of Pompey who became dictator of Rome before his assassination in front of a statue of Pompey.",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of outlaws that targeted Roman shipping and which Pompey fought in the Mediterranean.",
          "answer": "pirates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title held by Pompey three times, the highest elected position in Rome.",
          "answer": "consul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Celebration undertaken by Pompey three times, granted when soldiers acclaimed their general as imperator.",
          "answer": "triumph"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ally of Pompey and member of the First Triumvirate who died fighting the Parthians at the Battle of Carrhae.",
          "answer": "Marcus Licinius Crassus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Region that Pompey conquered from Mithridates the Great. It was home to the Kingdoms of Pontus and Bithynia on the eastern end of Rome’s territory.",
          "answer": [
            "Asia Minor or Anatolia",
            "Pontus if given before you read it"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman law that gave Pompey the power to defeat the aforementioned Mediterannean outlaws.",
          "answer": "Lex Gabinia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebellious general in Hispania that Pompey fought at the beginning of his career. He successfully waged a guerrila war against Rome.",
          "answer": "Quintus Sertorius"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Egypt",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Title given to the rulers of ancient Egypt.",
          "answer": "pharaoh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Primary Egyptian river that flooded during the season of Akhet.",
          "answer": "Nile River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Boy king whose tomb was re-discovered by Howard Carter in 1922.",
          "answer": "King Tutankhamun"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stone dedicated to Ptolemy V that was used to decipher hieroglyphics.",
          "answer": "Rosetta Stone"
        },
        {
          "question": "1274 BC battle against the Hittites, the largest chariot battle in history.",
          "answer": "Battle of Kadesh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document that provides instructions for those being judged by Ma’at.",
          "answer": "Egyptian Book of the Dead"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massive rock temples of Ramesses the Great and Nefertari built in Nubia.",
          "answer": "Abu Simbel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ruler who briefly succeeded Akhenaten, but who may actually just have been Nefertiti disguised as a man.",
          "answer": "Smenkhare or Smenkhkare"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Council of Trent",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Church, led by popes, that convened the Council.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "Movement, led by Martin Luther, that the Council sought to address.",
          "answer": "Protestant Reformation"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy Roman Emperor who demanded a council be held, some 20 years after he sacked Rome.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles V",
            "Charles I of Spain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of rites, including Baptism and the Eucharist, that the Council re-affirmed.",
          "answer": "seven sacraments"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin translation of the Bible that was named the official canon at the Council.",
          "answer": "Vulgate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Fourth century saint who created most of that Latin translation of the Bible.",
          "answer": "Saint Jerome"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lutheran concept that “works” are not necessary to receive God’s pardon.",
          "answer": "justification by faith alone or sola fide"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who originally convened the Council in 1545.",
          "answer": "Paul III"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Greek Combat",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Long race named in honor of a 490 BC Greek victory over Persia.",
          "answer": [
            "Marathon",
            "Battle of Marathon"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek kingdom ruled by the conquerors Alexander the Great and his father, Philip II.",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Military formation of troops and hoplites armed with spears and shields, the basic infantry unit in ancient Greece.",
          "answer": "phalanx"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of victory in which the winning side endures unsustainable casualties, named after an ancient commander who won at Asculum and Heraclea.",
          "answer": [
            "Pyrrhic Victory",
            "Pyrrhus of Epirus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of galley that formed the bulk of the Athenian navy, named for its three rows of oars.",
          "answer": "trireme"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek city state whose army, including the Sacred Band, executed one of the first flanking maneuvers over Sparta at the Battle of Leuctra [look-tra].",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander who won the battles of Leuctra and Mantinea [man-ti-nay-uh].",
          "answer": "Epaminondas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Long, pike-like spear introduced by Philip II to replace the dory in his armies.",
          "answer": "sarissa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Six Day War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Global organization that was led by U Thant during the war and which withdrew forces prior to the war.",
          "answer": "United Nations"
        },
        {
          "question": "Egyptian peninsula, east of the Red Sea, that was seized by Israel.",
          "answer": "Sinai Peninsula"
        },
        {
          "question": "Set of heights that Israel seized from Syria during the war.",
          "answer": "Golan Heights"
        },
        {
          "question": "Straits on the Gulf of Aqaba that Egypt closed to Israeli shipping, triggering the war.",
          "answer": "Straits of Tiran"
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of military action that Israel performed in Operation Focus to open the war.",
          "answer": "pre-emptive air strike"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli line of fortifications built along the Suez Canal after the war; it was overrun in 1973.",
          "answer": "Bar Lev Line"
        },
        {
          "question": "American research ship that was attacked by Israel in a friendly fire incident during the war.",
          "answer": "USS Liberty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Israeli Prime Minister during the war; he died in office two years later.",
          "answer": "Levi Eshkol"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Battle of Actium",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Egyptian queen whose ships’ hasty retreat signaled a turn in the battle.",
          "answer": "Cleopatra VII Philopator"
        },
        {
          "question": "Losing general at Actium, the Roman lover of that Egyptian queen.",
          "answer": "Marc Antony or Marcus Antonius"
        },
        {
          "question": "Winning general who took the title “Princeps” after the battle.",
          "answer": [
            "Octavian",
            "Gaius Octavius Thurinus",
            "Caesar Augustus",
            "Augustus Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epic poem by Virgil whose protagonist’s shield features a depiction of the battle.",
          "answer": "Aeneid"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that names the 34 BC “donations” in which Roman and Parthian land was divided up, a key cause of the war.",
          "answer": "Donations of Alexandria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of the Egyptian queen who was executed two weeks after his mother’s death.",
          "answer": "Caesarion or Ptolemy Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gulf in the Ionian Sea at whose opening the battle was fought.",
          "answer": "Ambracian Gulf"
        },
        {
          "question": "Admiral who commanded the victorious fleet at Actium, after which he built the first Pantheon.",
          "answer": "Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Boudica",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Roman territory where Boudica’s rebels sacked Londinium in modern England.",
          "answer": "Roman Britain or Britannia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman emperor at the start of the conquest of Boudica’s homeland in 43 AD.",
          "answer": [
            "Claudius",
            "Tiberius Claudius Caesar Augustus Germanicus, but do not"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman historian of Agricola whose Annals discusses Boudica’s revolt.",
          "answer": "Publius Cornelius Tacitus or Gaius Cornelius Tacitus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Celtic tribe that allied with Rome until they revolted under Boudica.",
          "answer": "Iceni"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Roman province that Boudica’s forces torched before sacking Londinium.",
          "answer": "Camulodunum"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle that ended Boudica’s revolt, named for a Roman road’s more modern name.",
          "answer": "Battle of Watling Street"
        },
        {
          "question": "Roman governor whose forces were severely outnumbered by Boudica’s at that battle, but won anyway.",
          "answer": [
            "Gaius Suetonius Paulinus",
            "either",
            "both underlined names"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Husband of Boudica whose will was ignored by the Romans, triggering her revolt.",
          "answer": "Prasutagus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alexander the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Greek kingdom he ruled from Pella before launching his conquests",
          "answer": "Macedonia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Father of Alexander who defeated Thebes at the Battle of Chaeronea",
          "answer": "Philip II of Macedon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Founder of the Lyceum who tutored him in his youth",
          "answer": "Aristotle"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in India where he defeated King Porus",
          "answer": "Battle of the Hydaspes River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Horse he rode for eighteen years who died at that battle",
          "answer": "Bucephalus ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term given to his successors who fought a series of wars that ended in 281 BC",
          "answer": "Diadochi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Persian satrap whom he had killed for betraying Darius III",
          "answer": [
            "Bessus",
            "Artaxerxes V"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City under the command of Batis which he was able to seize using tactics perfected at the Siege of Tyre",
          "answer": "Gaza 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 2"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "National Anthems",
      "prompt": "Which country has the national anthem...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"God Save the Queen,\" which is played at Wimbledon",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"The Star-Spangled Banner,\" which was written at Fort McHenry",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"La Marseillaise,\" or the \"War Song for the Army of the Rhine\"",
          "answer": "France or French Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Jana Gana Mana,\" [[JAN-ah GAN-ah MAN-ah]] which was written in Bengali by Rabindranath Tagore [[TAY-gohr]]",
          "answer": "Republic of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Marcha Real,\" whose lyrics were abolished after the death of Francisco Franco",
          "answer": "Kingdom of Spain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Maamme, [[MAH-may]] which is sung in either two or three verses depending on the presence of Swedes",
          "answer": "Republic of Finland"
        },
        {
          "question": "\"Wilhelmus,\" which is a first person account of a prince from Nassau",
          "answer": [
            "The Netherlands",
            "Holland"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "\"March of the Volunteers,\" which is addressed to all who do not wish to be slaves",
          "answer": [
            "People's Republic of China",
            "PRC",
            "or Zhonghua"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Ottoman Empire",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of the Republic of Turkey which grew out of the Ottoman Empire",
          "answer": "Ankara"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of knights that grew out of a medical institution who stopped the Ottoman conquest of Malta",
          "answer": [
            "Knights Hospitaller",
            "Order of Saint John"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sultan called \"the Magnificent\" who led the empire to its greatest extent",
          "answer": [
            "Suleiman I",
            "Suleiman the Magnificent",
            "Suleiman the Lawgiver"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1526 battle which that ruler won to complete the Ottoman conquest of Hungary",
          "answer": "Battle of Mohács ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who conquered Tunis in 1534, one year after being appointed Grand admiral of the Ottoman navy",
          "answer": [
            "Hayreddin Barbarossa",
            "Hizir Reis",
            "Hizir Hayrettin Pasha"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sultanate founded by slave soldiers in Egypt which was overthrown by the Ottomans in 1517",
          "answer": "Mamluk Sultanate"
        },
        {
          "question": "1522 siege at which the Ottomans expelled Catholic forces from the largest Dodecanese island",
          "answer": "Siege of Rhodes"
        },
        {
          "question": "16th and 17th century period during which the empire was essentially ruled by the wives and mothers of the sultan",
          "answer": "Sultanate of Women or Kadinlar Saltanati 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 5"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Crisis of the Third Century",
      "prompt": "Concerning the chaotic third century AD, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Hegemonic empire which split into three distinct sections during the Crisis of the Third Century.",
          "answer": [
            "Roman Empire or Rome",
            "Imperium Rōmānum"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Popular religious group persecuted by Emperor Diocletian.",
          "answer": "Christians"
        },
        {
          "question": "Elite Roman guards who killed emperors such as Pupienus [[poo-pee-AY-nus]], Balbinus, and Maximus Thrax.",
          "answer": "Praetorian Guard or Cohortēs praetōriae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Silver currency of Rome which was debased during the early crisis and virtually abandoned by the reign of Gordian III.",
          "answer": [
            "Denarii",
            "Denarius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty of emperors whose members included Septimius and Caracalla, whose downfall coincided with the crisis.",
          "answer": "Severan Dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "General and eventual emperor whose string of military victories led to the end of the crisis and his being crowned \"Restorer of the World.\"",
          "answer": "Aurelian or Lucius Domitius Aurelianus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dalmatian province of Rome that produced a series of emperors during the crisis, such as Decius and Probus.",
          "answer": [
            "Illyricum",
            "Roman Illyria"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Term originally used for cities bound by treaty that referred to barbarian mercenaries whose influence grew during the crisis.",
          "answer": [
            "Foederati",
            "Foederatus"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ancient Troy",
      "prompt": "Concerning the legendary city of Troy, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Modern-day nation where the ruins of Troy were discovered.",
          "answer": "Republic of Turkey or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti"
        },
        {
          "question": "Blind poet who described Troy in the Iliad.",
          "answer": [
            "Homer",
            "Homeros"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Legendary King of Troy and father of Hector who names treasures smuggled out of it by westerners.",
          "answer": [
            "King Priam",
            "Priam's Treasure"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "or 1200s BCE.",
          "answer": [
            "Mycenaeans",
            "Mycenaean Greece"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Confederation of raiders whose invasion of New Kingdom Egypt may have been assisted by Western Anatolian people like the Trojans.",
          "answer": "Sea Peoples"
        },
        {
          "question": "Amateur German archeologist who discovered Troy in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Heinrich Schliemann ]"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dead Anatolian language likely spoken by the inhabitants of Troy's sixth archaeological layer, and which is closely related to Hittite.",
          "answer": "Luwian"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek ceramic containers whose decline in quantity indicated a regression of Troy's trade near the end of its seventh layer.",
          "answer": [
            "Pithoi",
            "Pithos"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man names a theorem presented in Book XIII [“eight”] of Euclid’s Elements that\nrelates the products of diagonal lengths for a cyclic quadrilateral to products of side\nlengths. He also names a (20 pts) ",
        "list of ancient kings and their chronology that orders rulers\nbetween the Babylonian empire and the Roman empire. This man added a “crank\nmechanism” to Hipparchus’ notions of (10 pts) ",
        "deferent and epicycle. For 10 points, name this\nAlexandrian polymath who names the geocentric model of the universe, and who wrote the\nAlmagest [ALL-muh-jest]."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Ptolemy",
        "Claudius Ptolemy"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In response to a rebellion sparked by one of these events, Narses distributed gold to its\nspectators. Participants in these events used the biga [BEE-guh] or the quadriga [quodREEG-uh]. An uprising that started during one of these events sought to crown (20 pts) ",
        "Hypatius as the new emperor. These events, which were attended by groups such as the\nBlues, Greens, and Whites, were the origin of the Nika [NEEK-uh] Riots against (10 pts) ",
        "Justinian. They were held at the Hippodrome in Constantinople and the Circus Maximus in\nRome. For 10 points, name these contests that involved carts pulled by horses."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Roman chariot races",
        "chariot races",
        "Byzantine chariot races"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler interrupted a campaign to visit the oracle of Amun [ah-moon] at the Siwa\noasis. After this man’s death, his general Perdiccas [purr-dih-kahs] served as regent.\nDuring his father’s victory at the Battle of Chaeronea, this man commanded the (20 pts) ",
        "Companion Cavalry. His troops refused to go further after this man’s costly victory at the\nHydaspes River. This man was victorious at the Battle of Gaugamela [gog-ah-meh-luh]\nagainst Darius III, and founded a city (10 pts) ",
        "named after himself in Egypt. For 10 points, name\nthis Macedonian king who conquered land as far as India."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alexander the Great",
        "Alexander III",
        "Alexander III of Macedon",
        "Alexandros hos Megas"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Ancient gods worshiped by this ethnic group included Uzza [ooz-ah] and Hubal. It\nfought the Byzantine Empire at the Battle of Yarmouk. This ethnic group’s rebellion was\nsubdued in the Wars of Apostasy, after which their invasions brought down the (20 pts) ",
        "Sassanid [sass-uh-nihd] Empire. This ethnic group loyally followed the Rashidun [rash-eedone] after being subdued by (10 pts) ",
        "Abu Bakr [ah-boo bah-kur], and originally pledged loyalty to\na prophet who took dictation from Gabriel in a cave. For 10 points, name this largely Islamic\nethnic group that populates a peninsula northeast of Africa."
      ],
      "answer": "Arabs"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s reputation was hurt by a Chenango County trial in which he stood accused of fraudulent gold-digging. Lilburn Boggs’ “extermination order” drove him from Missouri to Illinois, where he renamed the city of “Commerce” after the (20 pts)",
        "Hebrew word for “Beautiful Place.” A mob in Carthage, Illinois murdered this founder of (10 pts)",
        "Nauvoo along with his brother Hyrum in 1844. In 1823, the angel Moroni guided this man to a set of “golden plates” in Reformed Egyptian. For 10 points, name this founder of Mormonism."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Smith, Jr."
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Traditionally, this empire was founded in 802 AD after one of its rulers completed a ceremony celebrating freedom from Javanese control. One ruler of this kingdom conquered parts of the (20 pts)",
        "Malay Peninsula, but lost wars to the neighboring states of Champa and Dai Viet. That ruler, Suryavarman II, portrayed himself as Vishnu in a (10 pts)",
        "monumental temple complex that was completed after his death. For 10 points, name this empire that built Angkor Wat and lent its name to a 20th century Communist group in Cambodia."
      ],
      "answer": "Khmer Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire’s only colonial possession, located in Tianjin, was granted in return for their meager participation in the Eight-Nation Alliance. The “Basic State Act” of this empire supposedly recognized all of its ethnic groups, although the status of languages as (20 pts)",
        "“customary” was often debated. This empire suffered embarrassingly large losses in the Brusilov offensive. A member of the Black (10 pts)",
        "Hand assassinated this empire’s Archduke Franz Ferdinand in 1914, provoking the First World War. For ten points, name this dual-monarchy led by the Hapsburg dynasty until its dissolution in 1918."
      ],
      "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Kahun and the Edwin Smith papyruses were early Egyptian texts related to this discipline, the latter of which may have been written by Djoser’s chancellor Imhotep. Thomas Percival wrote the first text outlining the ethics required in this discipline, which was further advanced in the post-Holocaust (20 pts)",
        "Nuremberg Code. A 1928 discovery by Alexander Fleming revolutionized this discipline, whose practitioners are advised to (10 pts)",
        "“do no harm” by an ancient Greek text. The Hippocratic Oath governs, for ten points, what discipline that seeks to prevent and treat disease?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "medicine",
        "equivalents and descriptions, such as doctoring"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After one victory, this ruler’s forces caught the enemy horka, Bulcsu, and executed him. This ruler requested his son to be married to a Byzantine princess, Theophanu. This ruler had Pope Leo VIII elected after his predecessor entered negotiations with the son of Berengar II. Liudolf of (20 pts)",
        "Swabia led a revolt against this ruler after his marriage to Adelaide of Italy. This son of Henry the Fowler was crowned by (10 pts)",
        "Pope John XII seven years after his forces defeated the Magyars at the Battle of Lechfeld. For ten points, name this first Germanic Holy Roman Emperor."
      ],
      "answer": "Otto I, Holy Roman Emperor"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader issued the seisachtheia [says-ACK-the-uh], which cancelled debts and ended slave labor as a means of paying debts. He organized the boule as a council of 400 citizens, who were eligible to serve if they produced 200 medimnoi of goods or more; that council was expanded to 500 by (20 pts)",
        "Cleisthenes [KLICE-the-nees]. The power of the Areopagus was reduced by this man’s reforms, which preserved (10 pts)",
        "Draco’s punishments for homicide. For ten points, name this leader who reformed the Athenian constitution in the early 6th century BC."
      ],
      "answer": "Solon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing general of this battle “had not despaired of the Republic” after escaping with seventy horsemen. In the aftermath of this battle, Tarentum and Capua revoked their allegiance with the loser. The winning side placed (20 pts)",
        "Celtic and Spanish forces in the center, where they pulled back, allowing hidden, experienced Libyan soldiers to entrap the losing army in a double-envelopment. Gaius Terentius Varro survived this battle, though (10 pts)",
        "70,000 Romans did not. Victories at Trebia and Lake Trasimene were followed by a massive defeat at, for ten points, what 216 BC battle in southern Italy, a massive tactical victor for Hannibal?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Cannae"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Two answers required. The fleets of these two nations joined up to defeat Andrea Doria at Ponza. Fears of Habsburg expansion after Charles V’s capture of Tunis led (20 pts)",
        "Jean de la Forest to negotiate a military treaty between these two nations. These two nations faced each other in the Battle of the Pyramids during the Egyptian campaign, which marked the end of the 1536 (10 pts)",
        "“Unholy Alliance” signed by Francis I and Suleiman the Magnificent. For ten points, name these two European empires, led by Napoleon and Sultan Selim III."
      ],
      "answer": "France and the Ottoman Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This school of philosophy argued that purely incorporeal “being” did not exist and divided the world into four categories, including “substance” and “quality.” The concept of adiaphora, or actions outside the realm of morality, was (20 pts)",
        "first propounded by this school of thought. One proponent of this school of thought frequently encouraged himself to “Erase impressions!” and wrote his (10 pts)",
        "Meditations while on a military campaign. Zeno of Citium founded, for ten points, what school of Ancient Greek thought, followed by Marcus Aurelius, that stressed virtue and freedom from emotion?"
      ],
      "answer": "Stoicism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Academic Legion toppled a government in this empire when Franz von Pillersdorf failed to repeal censorship laws. This empire lost possession of Lombardy in the Treaty of Villafranca during the Italian Wars of Independence. Following (20 pts)",
        "Francis I’s defeat at Austerlitz and the ensuing Treaty of Pressburg, the Holy Roman Empire was effectively reorganized as this empire. In 1867, this empire entered into the (10 pts)",
        "Ausgleich dual-monarchy under Franz Joseph I. For ten points, name this empire that merged with Hungary in the 19th century."
      ],
      "answer": "Austrian Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire attempted to defuse ethnic tension in its west via the “Basic State Act,” equally recognized all languages. Unity within this empire was symbolized with the abbreviation k.u.k., indicating its (20 pts)",
        "“imperial and royal” nature. This empire was formed after Gyula Andrassy and Ferenc Deak negotiated a Compromise of 1867, and it was drawn into a (10 pts)",
        "war after assassins from the Black Hand killed Archduke Franz Ferdinand. For ten points, name this dual monarchy based in Vienna and Budapest that dissolved near the end of World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Austria-Hungary"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A turning point in this period was the Battle of Naissus; a cavalry commander at that battle later defeated the Palmyrenes, a breakaway empire that formed during this period. Postumus’s Gallic Empire was also defeated by Aurelian near the end of this period, which began with the (20 pts)",
        "Year of the Six Emperors and ended with the rule of Diocletian. Numerous generals took the imperial throne during this period, in which economic (10 pts)",
        "breakdown ruined life on the frontier. For ten points, name this century in which the Roman Empire nearly fell completely apart."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Crisis of the Third Century AD",
        "CE"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With the Slavs and the Avars, this empire led a 638 Siege of Constantinople against Heraclius. This empire collapsed to the Islamic Caliphate during Yazdegerd III’s reign. Emperor Valerian I was captured and turned into a human (20 pts)",
        "footstool after the Battle of Edessa by this empire’s King Shapur I. This empire ruled from Ctesiphon signed a Treaty of Eternal Peace with the (10 pts)",
        "Byzantine Emperor Justinian I. Khosrau the Great ruled, for ten points, what Persian empire that succeeded the Parthian Empire and continued to fight Rome?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sassanid Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While Aristophanes of Byzantium led one of these facilities, he invented the diacritical marks used in the Greek language; Aristarchus of Samothrace later led that one of these facilities. When one of these facilities was excavated in (20 pts)",
        "Ashurbanipal’s palace, its discoveries were mixed with tablets found in Sennacherib’s palace, rendering the true discovery location of the (10 pts)",
        "Epic of Gilgamesh a mystery. For ten points, name this type of location that Julius Caesar burned in Alexandria, causing the loss of thousands of papyrus scrolls and their educational contents."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "ancient library",
        "Library of Alexandria",
        "Library of Ashurbanipal after his name is mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s winning side took the Boedromia festival, which celebrated Theseus beating the Amazons, and changed it to celebrate this victory. A delay in this battle was prompted when it was found that reinforcements could not come until the (20 pts)",
        "Karneia [kar-nye-uh] festival ended. The winning side in this battle struck after Callimachus broke a tied vote in favor of attacking, thus turning back an invasion sent by (10 pts)",
        "Darius the Great. Athens prevailed over the Persian Empire in, for ten points, what 490 BC battle whose result was reported by Pheidippides after running 26 miles?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Housesteads is a particularly well-preserved fort along this structure, whose milecastles were typically flanked by two turrets. A series of tablets were found near this structure’s fort of Vindolanda. The River (20 pts)",
        "Tyne was the starting point of this structure, which terminated at Solway Firth. This structure, whose construction started in 122 AD, was intended to (10 pts)",
        "keep out the Picts and Britons from the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this defensive structure, built by a namesake Roman Emperor who succeeded Trajan."
      ],
      "answer": "Hadrian’s Wall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This empire was victorious at the Battle of Avarayr against the Armenians, but granted them freedom of religion anyway. During a lengthy peace known as the Intermediate Era, this empire’s Yazdegerd I ended its persecution of Christians. A ruler of this empire allegedly flayed and (20 pts)",
        "dyed the skin of his rival vermillion after winning the Battle of Edessa against Valerian. This empire was founded after (10 pts)",
        "Artabanus V was defeated by Ardashir. Shapur the Great ruled, for ten points, what Persia-based empire that succeeded the Parthians?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sassanid Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to legend, because a ruler of this empire asked for the head of the Maharaja of Zabag, the ruler’s head was instead taken by the Maharaja. Rajendra Chola helped this empire defeat the Tambralinga Kingdom and the Srivijayas in the (20 pts)",
        "11th century. The Baphuon temple and Baray water resevoirs were built by this empire. The diplomat Zhou Daguan was sent to this empire, traveling through (10 pts)",
        "Tonle Sap lake. Several kings named Jayavarman ruled, for ten points, what empire that built Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia?"
      ],
      "answer": "Khmer Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This philosopher, who described a compound of matter and form which he termed hylomorphism, divided tragic theater into elements such as opsis, mythos, and ethos in what is believed to be the first work of (20 pts)",
        "literary theory. This philosopher fled Athens in 323 BC after the death of his patron king. (10 pts)",
        "Poetics, Metaphysics, and the Nicomachean Ethics were written by, for ten points, what Greek philosopher, a student of Plato who tutored Alexander the Great?"
      ],
      "answer": "Aristotle"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader defeated the Helvetii at the Battle of Bibracte and the Nervii at the Battle of the Sabis. This man, who was rumored to have had an affair with King Nicomedes in his youth, was once captured by a group of (20 pts)",
        "pirates who he later had crucified. Vercingetorix was defeated at the siege of (10 pts)",
        "Alesia by this man, who legendarily declared “the die is cast” upon crossing the Rubicon to instigate a civil war. For ten points, name this Roman dictator who was assassinated by conspirators on the Ides of March."
      ],
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A king of this empire issued coinage that featured the motto “May this please the people.” Zoscales was listed as the leader of this empire in the Periplus of the Erythraean Sea. This exporter of ivory traded extensively with the Himyarites of (20 pts)",
        "Yemen. A tutor to a king of this empire named Frumentius became the first head of this empire’s church after it converted to Christianity in the (10 pts)",
        "fourth century. The capital of this empire is said to contain the Ark of the Covenant, and it was located along the Red Sea. For ten points, name this early African Empire in modern-day Eritrea and Ethiopia."
      ],
      "answer": "Kingdom of Axum"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this empire named Alexander died of exhaustion after playing tzykanisterion [[tzik-an-ih-STEER-ee-on]], a form of polo. This empire was defended by strongholds called al-thughur [[al THOO-goor]] between it and the (20 pts)",
        "Umayyads and Abbasids. This empire faced Leo of Tripoli's sack while \"Oleg the Prophet\" attacked its capital, leading to a 911 treaty with the Rus. (10 pts)",
        "Leo VI the Wise and Basil the Bulgar-Slayer ruled, for ten points, what empire from Constantinople?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Byzantine Empire",
        "Byzantines",
        "Eastern Roman Empire",
        "do not",
        "or"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) States surrounding this one were called Limitrophe [[LEE-meh-trohf]] states which formed the cordon sanitaire [[kor-DONH sahn-ee-TEHR]]. Territorial parts of this country underwent \"korenization.\" Winston Churchill (20 pts)",
        "handed over political control of satellite states to this country in his Mediterranean Strategy, via the Percentages Agreement which left Greece to the Western allies while forsaking (10 pts)",
        "Bulgaria and Romania to communism. For ten points, name this country which was led by Josef Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "Soviet Union"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) British forces captured Mahmoud Fehmy in this country and attacked their opponents at Kassassin. Prince Arthur, the son of Queen Victoria, led a bayonet charge under Garnet Wolseley's command in this country for which William Marsh Edwards won a Victoria Cross. This country, the site of the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Tel El Kebir, was the location of Richard Eve's defense of Ahmed 'Urabi. In 1919, Saad Zaghlul led this country's Wafd party to rebel. Once governed by (10 pts)",
        "Muhammad Ali, for ten points, what is this country, considered geographically to be in both Africa and Asia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arab Republic of Egypt",
        "Khedivate of Egypt",
        "Sultanate of Egypt",
        "Ottoman Egypt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While pretending to be this man, Terentius Maximus was supported by Artabanus III, while another pseudo-imposter of this man was likely a slave from Pontus [[PONT-shus]] who traveled to Kythnos [[SITH-nos]]. This man's army captured (20 pts)",
        "Artaxata [[ahr-tah-KSAH-tah]], defeating Vologases I and installing Tigranes in Armenia. During his rule, this man faced Vindex's rebellion and ended Boudica's revolt. This man's death sparked the (10 pts)",
        "Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this tyrannical Roman emperor who likely did not fiddle when Rome burned."
      ],
      "answer": "Nero 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 6"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A false bomb threat was leveraged by this national government to arrest dissident journalist Raman Pratasevich in June 2021. Opposition leader Sergei (20 pts)",
        "Tikhanovsky [[teek-hah-NOHV-skee]] was sentenced to jail for eighteen years in response to his plan to challenge a president of this country seeking his sixth term. The Anti-Cockroach Movement opposed longtime president Alexander (10 pts)",
        "Lukashenko [[loo-kah-SHEN-koh]] in, for ten points, what Eastern European nation governed from Minsk?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Belarus or Respublika Belarus",
        "Byelorussia"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In Medieval England, the eggs of this specific animal were fed to children to ward off drunkenness and as a cure to blindness. One of these animals named Ko'Ko, or the \"Watcher of the dark,\" is the underworld deity of the Hopi. A contingent of this specific bird flying over the battle site of (20 pts)",
        "Salamis signaled a Greek victory over the Persians according to Plutarch. The Athenian tetradrachma depicts this (10 pts)",
        "bird and symbol of the city on its backside. For ten points, name this bird which symbolized wisdom in Ancient Greece and is associated with Athena."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Owls or Strigiformes",
        "Athene noctua",
        "or Owl of Athena",
        "Owl of Minerva"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This unit hacked through the Pecheneg nomads' laager formation, which proved vital in John II's victory at the Battle of Beroia [[beh-roh-EE-ah]]. The capture and ransom of Romanos (20 pts)",
        "IV Diogenes led these people to organize a palace coup upon his return to the capital. By the rule of Alexios Komnenos, this force was heavily composed of Anglo-Saxon (10 pts)",
        "refugees from Norman England. For ten points, name this elite guard of the Byzantine Empire originally made up of Norsemen."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Varangian Guard or Varyags",
        "Tágma tōn Varángōn"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man's father, Celtillus, was put to death for attempting to rule all of his homeland, and this man's main efforts were preceded by the revolt of Ambiorix. This Arverni nobleman successfully provided misinformation to the (20 pts)",
        "Aedui tribe, resulting in their cavalry being attacked by the allied Roman legion at Gergovia. This man was ritually strangled at the Temple of Jupiter after his imprisonment following a loss at the Siege of (10 pts)",
        "Alesia. For ten points, name this leader of the confederation that was defeated by Julius Caesar during the Roman conquest of Gaul."
      ],
      "answer": "Vercingetorix ]"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Client-king Artabazos I of Phrygia [[frih-JEE-ah]] intentionally withheld his troops from participating in this battle, successfully retreating with his men to Ionia. The sole survivor of the \"300\" from (20 pts)",
        "Thermopylae, Aristodemus [[ah-ree-STOH- deh-mus]], was slain at this battle while attempting to redeem himself. According to legend, the Persian general Mardonius (10 pts)",
        "lost his life in this battle after a Spartan warrior smashed his skull with a rock. For ten points, name this final land battle during the second Persian invasion of Greece, which ended with a decisive Greek victory."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Plataea"
    }
  ]
}